# Julia H. Yang, Ph.D.

Environmental Fellow, Harvard University

jhyang@g.harvard.edu | (631) 312-7365 Website: juliayang.github.io (she/her/hers)

# SUMMARY

I am a **computational materials scientist** focused on **sustainability** challenges in **energy storage**. My research advances and applies first-principles and machine learning approaches to navigate chemical space and design urgently-needed materials for **energy and the environment**.

### EDUCATION

### Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Environmental Fellow

July 2022 -present

- Postdoctoral advisor: Prof. Boris Kozinsky
- Independent research proposal funded through Harvard University Center for the Environment

### University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, CA

Ph.D. in Materials Science & Engineering

Aug. 2016-May 2022

- Thesis advisor: Prof. Gerbrand Ceder
- Thesis: Computational Understanding of Ionic Systems for Advanced Energy Storage Materials
- Minors: Physics, Statistics

### Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, PA

B.S. in Materials Science & Engineering, additional major in Physics

Aug. 2012-May 2016

- Honors research advisor: Prof. Elias Towe
- Honors project: Thermal Transport in Two-Dimensional Monolayer Semiconductors

# EXPERIENCE

## Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Environmental Fellow, John A. Paulson School of Engineering and Applied Sciences

July 2022 -present

- Advised by: Prof. Boris Kozinsky
- Use density functional theory, computational chemistry, and machine learning to model thermal and electrochemical stability of explicit solvents
- Experimental collaboration with Park group (Columbia University)
- 4 journal publications in preparation (1 first-author/corresponding author)

#### Columbia University

New York City, NY

Postdoctoral Fellow, Fu Foundation School of Engineering and Applied Science

July 2022 -Aug. 2022

- Advised by: Prof. Ah-Hyung Alissa Park
- Applied electrochemical methods to study electrodeposition of critical materials in organic solvents

### University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, CA

Graduate Student Researcher, Department of Materials Science & Engineering

Aug. 2016 -May 2022

- Advised by: Prof. Gerbrand Ceder

- Advanced coupled cluster expansion lattice models to study high energy and high power density lithium-ion battery electrodes
- Evaluated phase stability in earth-abundant electrodes using first-principles calculations
- Rationalized origin of systematic error in density functional theory approximations for ionic systems
- 13 journal publications (5 first or co-first author, 1 corresponding author)

# X (formerly Google X), the Moonshot Factory

Mountain View, CA May 2021 –Sept 2021

AI Resident

- Advised by: Dr. Alexander Holiday

- Developed machine learning platform to optimize chemical recycling of waste plastics
- 4 filed patents (1 first-author patent)

# Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory

Laurel, MD

Technical Aide

May 2016 –July 2016

- Performed optical analysis of stray photon emission from discarded field-programmable gate arrays for hardware espionage
- Developed experimental setup used in a NASA mission proposal

### Honors & Awards

• NextProf Nexus at Georgia Institute of Technology	Aug. 2023
• Harvard University Center for the Environment Environmental Fellow	$July\ 2022July\ 2024$
• National Defense Science and Engineering Graduate Fellow	Aug. 2016–Aug. 2019
• Carnegie Mellon University University Honors	May 2016
• Carnegie Mellon University College of Engineering Honors	May 2016
• Carnegie Mellon University Senior Leadership Award	May 2016
• U.C. Berkeley Materials Science & Engineering Rising Star Scholarship	Awarded Jan. 2016
• Semiconductor Research Corporation Undergraduate Fellowship	Jan. 2014–May 2016
• Tau Beta Pi Engineering Honors Society	May 2015

# Publications

- [1] R. Kam, K. Jun, L. Barroso-Luque, <u>J. H. Yang</u>, F. Xie, and G. Ceder, "Crystal structures and phase stability of the  $Li_2S$ - $P_2S_5$  system from first principles", (submitted).
- [2] J. H. Yang† and G. Ceder†, "Activated internetwork pathways in partially-disordered spinel cathode materials with ultrahigh rate performance", Adv. Energy Mater., vol. 13, no. 4, p. 2202955, 2023. DOI: 10.1002/aenm.202202955.
- [3] Z. Jadidi, J. H. Yang, T. Chen, L. Barroso-Luque, and G. Ceder, "Ab-initio study of short-range ordering in vanadium-based disordered rocksalt structures", *J. Mater. Chem. A*, 2023, Advance Article. DOI: doi.org/10.1039/D3TA02475J.
- [4] L. Barroso-Luque, J. H. Yang, F. Xie, T. Chen, R. L. Kam, Z. Jadidi, P. Zhong, and G. Ceder, "Smol: A python package for cluster expansions and beyond", *J. Open Source Softw.*, vol. 7, no. 77, p. 4504, 2022. DOI: 10.21105/joss.04504.

- [5] L. Barroso-Luque, P. Zhong, J. H. Yang, F. Xie, T. Chen, B. Ouyang, and G. Ceder, "Cluster expansions of multicomponent ionic materials: Formalism and methodology", *Phys. Rev. B*, vol. 106, no. 14, p. 144 202, 2022. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevB.106.144202.
- [6] T. Chen, J. H. Yang, L. Barroso-Luque, and G. Ceder, "Removing the two-phase transition in spinel  $LiMn_2O_4$  through cation disorder", ACS Energy Lett., vol. 8, no. 1, pp. 314–319, 2022. DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02141.
- [7] J. H. Yang, T. Chen, L. Barroso-Luque, Z. Jadidi, and G. Ceder, "Approaches for handling high-dimensional cluster expansions of ionic systems", npj Comput. Mater., vol. 8, no. 1, p. 133, 2022. DOI: 10.1038/s41524-022-00818-3.
- [8] L. Barroso-Luque, J. H. Yang, and G. Ceder, "Sparse expansions of multicomponent oxide configuration energy using coherency and redundancy", *Phys. Rev. B*, vol. 104, p. 224 203, 22 2021. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevB.104.224203.
- [9] J. H. Yang, H. Kim, and G. Ceder, "Insights into Layered Oxide Cathodes for Rechargeable Batteries", *Molecules*, vol. 26, no. 11, 2021. DOI: 10.3390/molecules26113173.
- [10] H. Kim, D.-H. Kwon, J. C. Kim, B. Ouyang, H. Kim, <u>J. H. Yang</u>, and G. Ceder, "Na+ Redistribution by Electrochemical Na+/K+ Exchange in Layered Na<sub>x</sub>Ni<sub>2</sub>SbO<sub>6</sub>", Chem. Mater., vol. 32, no. 10, pp. 4312–4323, 2020. DOI: 10.1021/acs.chemmater.0c01152.
- [11] J. C. \*. Kim, D.-H. \*. Kwon, <u>J. H. Yang\*</u>, H. Kim, S.-H. Bo, L. Wu, H. Kim, D.-H. Seo, T. Shi, J. Wang, Y. Zhu, and G. Ceder, "Direct Observation of Alternating Octahedral and Prismatic Sodium Layers in O3-Type Transition Metal Oxides", *Adv. Energy Mater.*, vol. 10, no. 31, p. 2001 151, 2020. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1002/aenm.202001151.
- [12] J. H. Yang, D. A. Kitchaev, and G. Ceder, "Rationalizing accurate structure prediction in the meta-GGA SCAN functional", *Phys. Rev. B*, vol. 100, no. 3, p. 35132, 2019. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevB.100.035132.
- [13] Y. Zhang, D. A. Kitchaev, <u>J. H. Yang</u>, T. Chen, S. T. Dacek, R. A. Sarmiento-Pérez, M. A. L. Marques, H. Peng, G. Ceder, J. P. Perdew, and J. Sun, "Efficient first-principles prediction of solid stability: Towards chemical accuracy", *npj Comput. Mater.*, vol. 4, no. 1, p. 9, 2018. DOI: 10.1038/s41524-018-0065-z.
- [14] C. F. Brasz, J. H. Yang, and C. B. Arnold, "Tilting of adjacent laser-induced liquid jets", Microfluid. Nanofluid., vol. 18, no. 2, pp. 185–197, 2015. DOI: 10.1007/s10404-014-1429-4.

#### In preparation

- H. Yang, J. H. Yang, B. Kozinsky, and J. J. Vlassak, "Complex ion crosslinked on-demand-dissociable chitosan with extended working pH range".
- J. H. Yang†, A. W.-S. Ooi, Y. Xie, Z. A. Goodwin, J. Ding, S. Falletta, A.-H. A. Park, and B. Kozinsky†, "Thermal decomposition of the ethaline deep eutectic solvent".
- Z. A. Goodwin, J. H. Yang, M. B. Wenny, A. Cepellotti, A. Johansson, L. Sun, S. Batzner, A. Musaelian, J. A. Mason, N. Molinari, and B. Kozinsky, "Chemically accurate ionic liquid simulations via graph neural nets".
- D. Morgan, B. Kozinsky, V. Honavar, et al., "A Practical Guide to Machine Learning Potentials Status and Future".

<sup>\*</sup> equal contribution  $\mid$  † corresponding author  $\mid$  6 first-author  $\mid$  2 corresponding-author

# **PATENTS**

- [1] J. H. Yang, V. Gharakhanyan, T. Gadhiya, and A. Holiday, "Ionic liquid-based depolymerization optimization", U.S. Patent App. 17/967,711, filed Oct. 17, 2022.
- [2] T. Gadhiya, F. Shah, N. Vyas, V. Gharakhanyan, <u>J. H. Yang</u>, and A. Holiday, "Depolymerizeration optimization platform", U.S. Patent App. 17/967,723, filed Oct. 17, 2022.
- [3] V. Gharakhanyan, J. H. Yang, T. Gadhiya, and A. Holiday, "Search for candidate molecules using quantum or thermodynamic simulations and autoencoder", U.S. Patent App. 17/967,704, filed Oct. 17, 2022.
- [4] T. Ghadiya, F. Shah, N. Vyas, J. H. Yang, V. Gharakhanyan, and A. Holiday, "Molecular structure transformers for property prediction", U.S. Patent App. 17/967,685, filed Oct. 17, 2022.

# Oral Presentations

- [1] <u>J. H. Yang</u>, W.-S. A. Ooi, A.-H. A. Park, and B. Kozinsky, "Assessing thermal decomposition reactions in the ethaline green solvent using machine learned interatomic potentials", ACS Fall Meeting, August 13, 2023, San Francisco, CA.
- [2] J. H. Yang, W.-S. A. Ooi, K. Bystrom, A.-H. A. Park, and B. Kozinsky, "Computational Optimization of Nickel Metal Recovery from Li-ion Cathodes for a Circular Economy in Energy Storage", MRS Spring Meeting, April 12, 2023, San Francisco, CA.
- [3] J. H. Yang, K. Bystrom, and B. Kozinsky, "Understanding Metal Ion Interactions in Solvents Using First-Principles and Machine Learning Interatomic Potentials", APS March Meeting, March 6, 2023, Las Vegas, NV.
- [4] <u>J. H. Yang</u>. "Sustainability Challenges in Energy Storage Materials" (Invited), SOSV, a global venture capital firm, June 28, 2022, San Francisco, CA.
- [5] J. H. Yang. "Modeling high-component disordered systems for sustainable energy storage materials." U.C. Berkeley Materials Science and Engineering Spring Seminar, March 10, 2022, Berkeley, CA.
- [6] J. H. Yang and G. Ceder, "Ab initio Modeling of Configurational Disorder in Complex Systems by Combining Machine Learning and Cluster Expansions", MRS Fall Meeting, Nov. 29-Dec. 2, 2021, Cambridge, MA.
- [7] A. Holiday, J. H. Yang, V. Gharakhanyan, and T. Gadhiya. (Presentation title withheld due to non-disclosure agreements.) Google X Techforum, Oct. 12, 2021. Presented virtually.
- [8] J. H. Yang and G. Ceder. "Thermodynamics of Spinel-like Cation Partial Ordering in Ultrahigh Power and Energy Density Li-ion Batteries for Fast-Charging Electric Vehicles." PRiME 2020 (ECS, ECSJ, & KECS Joint Meeting), Oct. 4-9, 2020. Presented virtually.
- [9] J. H. Yang, D. A. Kitchaev, and G. Ceder, "Benchmarking the Structure Selection Performance of the SCAN Functional Relative to PBE and PBE-D3", APS March Meeting, March 4-8, 2019. Boston, MA

[10] J. H. Yang, C. F. Brasz, and C. B. Arnold, "Time-resolved Imaging Studies of Adjacent Liquid Jet Formation", APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Meeting, Nov. 24-26, 2013. Pittsburgh, PA.

## POSTER PRESENTATIONS

[1] J. H. Yang and G. Ceder, "Modeling high-component, disordered rocksalt (DRX) systems for high-energy density Li-ion rechargeable batteries", Gordon Research Conference on Batteries, Feb. 16-21, 2020. Ventura, CA.

# Teaching & Mentoring

• Guest lecturer on DFT   Carnegie Mellon University	April 2021
18-817: Fundamentals of Semiconductors and Nanostructures (graduate-level)	

• Graduate Student Instructor | U.C. Berkeley Aug. 2019–Dec. 2019 MSE–201A: Thermodynamics and Phase Transformations in Solids (graduate-level)

• Volunteer instructor | Berkeley High School Sept. 2016-May 2017 Berkeley Energy and Resources Collaborative High School Program

• Course Assistant | Carnegie Mellon University Sept. 2015—Dec. 2015 15-112: Fundamentals of Programming (undergraduate-level)

• Academic Development Peer Tutor | Carnegie Mellon University Jan. 2013–May 2016 All core MSE courses (undergraduate-level)

• Research Mentor 2017–present

Students mentored:

Whai-Shin Amanda Ooi, Ph.D. student, Columbia University Chemical Engineering

July 2022—present

Zinab Jadidi, Ph.D. student, U.C. Berkeley Materials Science & Engineering

March 2020—May 2022

Ryan Riddle, Master's student, U.C. Berkeley Computer Science

Sept. 2021—May 2018

# SERVICE

#### • Session chair

MRS Fall 2021 | Symposium CH04 | Accelerating Materials Characterization,

Modeling, and Discovery by Physics-Informed Machine Learning

ACS Fall 2023 | ACS Division of Computers In Chemisry | Materials Science I

ACS Fall 2023 | ACS Division of Computers In Chemisry | Drug Design

San Francisco, CA

San Francisco, CA

• Discussion leader

ACS Fall 2023 | What to Expect from Graduate School

San Francisco, CA

• Reviewer Mar. 2022–present

MRS Energy & Sustainability (1), npj Computational Materials (1), ACS Materials Letters (2)

# Proposals

#### • Harvard University

Two-year independent postdoctoral proposal funded by Harvard University Center for the Environment | Award: \$170,000.

July 2022-July 2024

# SKILLS

- Programming: Python, bash, R
- Computational: density functional theory, computational chemistry, Monte Carlo methods, cluster expansion method, molecular dynamics, machine learning interatomic potentials
- Experimental: Electrochemical analysis, laser induced forward transfer

### References

#### • Gerbrand Ceder

Samsung Distinguished Chair in Nanoscience and Nanotechnology Research Department of Materials Science and Engineering University of California, Berkeley gceder@berkeley.edu

#### Boris Kozinsky

Thomas D. Cabot Associate Professor of Computational Materials Science Harvard John A. Paulson School of Engineering and Applied Sciences Harvard University bkoz@seas.harvard.edu

### • Ah-Hyung Alissa Park

Ronald and Valerie Sugar Dean and Professor Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering University of California, Los Angeles apark@seas.ucla.edu

### • Alexander Holiday

Senior Machine Learning Engineer X, the Moonshot Factory Mountain View, CA aholiday@x.team